marina talked about separation and we've
been given an architecture or what I
call people behind it South Africa
blacks were separated from whites and
was considered human progress we have a
pause world view that very consciously
who didn't place a separation of
humanity from nature the Cartesian
laconian Newtonian world view of
reductionist mechanism and we be told
that's the only thing that's knowledge
and science and women's knowledge women
science indigenous knowledge was over
treated as not knowledge and the
interesting thing is bacon called it the
bulk of masculine time that the feminine
had to be exiled for that project whose
ultimate expressions are genetic
engineering synthetic biology
geo-engineering mess of the planet in
arrogance as marina mentioned and then
as if that wasn't enough when they
wanted to move money for war they put
another boundary the production boundary
if you consume what you produce then
you're not producing so the forest
doesn't reduce because it resizes its
nutrients and water we've been doing
produced because they produce for
nourishment of the household third world
essence don't produce because they
produce to consume and all our
production was wiped out in a goat and
then the instruments kept months of time
now we've got the amazing instruments of
terror to the derivatives collateral
debt obligations collateral that burn
their obligations kweli the cube if
we're going to make it to the power 4
and Wall Street collapsed the planetary
boundaries that are being violated
sick case of Agriculture the 320
boundaries that were mentioned
biodiversity climate change language and
only cause of a model of agriculture
based on narrow-minded thinking
ignorance about how the earth words and
a negation of all the production the
eighty percent food that's reaching the
tables of people forty percent
greenhouse gases are coming from that
kind of agriculture hunger is related
very intimately to that tanker capture
the quarter million Indian farmers have
been pushed to commit suicide because of
indebtedness because of that kind of
Agriculture if you really look at it is
that agriculture producing food know a
lot of it goes to run cars some of it
goes to torture animals hope you can't
call it animal feed Oh whines wanted
grass they didn't want so early
definitely not GM soya bean if you were
to ask even the stuff that comes out as
genetically modified corn and soya and
all the plans they create out of this I
got it non-food it's not worth eating
it's literally we have a beautifully
sanskrit word for it apart ship not
world consuming and giving content to
this they just think they is the
agriculture that women shape did not
lead to emissions of greenhouse gases
was more adaptive even false seeds that
are able to deal with the drought and
the cyclone and the flood now the
companies that started see patenting in
nineteen what happened
exactly what we were suffering earlier I
think someone can make us having a
translator is on the way thank you yes
yes thank you I'm sorry for the
frustration and um can be very
frustrating thank you for your patience
and thank you for translating so the
creation boundary denied the creativity
of nature in giving us the rich
biodiversity the creativity of women to
give us all the diversity of seeds and
now suddenly the only creators am on San
Jose and all they do is either steal our
seeds I'll put a toxic gene in it how
polluted should be punished according to
polluter pays principle and these should
be punished and we are rewarding them
with a monopoly on life 11 so I
celebrate the decision of the Supreme
Court of Brazil that ruled against
Monsanto on the case brought by peasants
or collections of royalties
they proceed freedom because we believe
the seed has freedom see this life life
has freedom farmers have the freedom to
save seeds and the lowers of Monsanto
are not going to come in the way of our
freedoms that's why I started navdanya
at 25 years ago when the WTO rules
started to be shaped to treat seed
saving and see Dex chain is a crime now
I'm not depressed than the text because
I didn't come here for a text I came
your personal ad man is not a document
it is the life of our rivers and assets
freedom does not grow out of bad taste I
think it grew up to the song Sheila sign
for us green is not the color of money
it is the color of life we are either
going to have a future where women lead
the way to make peace with the earth oh
we are not going to have a human future
at all one of the other divisions and
separations that was created under the
separation with the earth is to
constantly tell us if you don't destroy
the earth we don't meet human needs I
think we know the women now peasants
know the image earnest people know that
there is no separation between the
rights of the earth and the rights of
humanity if the river doesn't flow there
is no water and I old enough to have
lived a life when we could go to a
stream and the ganga river and drink
water as the tongue has been degraded
unlike as we locked up in plastic
Thanks huge money trillions of dollars
for the water bottle errs women in plant
Amanda porch back coca-cola was stealing
their water and shut the plant down
patent both authorities water and his
product of coca-cola the rights of the
bees and the earthworms and soil
organisms and the plants that feed us
are the same as the rights of the
farmers who produced moon and the rights
of every would-be who must eat we need a
leap the oldest people of our time and
women which show the way on how to do it
no amount of manipulated text no amount
of hijack governments know about amount
of stealing of our democracy is going to
stop us from creating this new freedom
movement for the earth and my humanity
hey you think